<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council Res. No. SI-R17-012">
  <heading>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO COUNCIL RESOLUTION NO. SI-R17-012</heading>
  <heading type="law">ACT AUTHORIZING FOURTH WITHDRAWAL OF AAMODT WATER SETTLEMENT TRUST FUNDS FROM THE OFFICE OF SPECIAL TRUSTEE TO FUND AAMODT SETTLEMENT IMPLEMENTATION ACTIVITIES REQUESTED BY PUEBLO IN COORDINATION WITH REGIONAL WATER SYSTEM WORK</heading>
  <meta>
    <effective>2017-05-25</effective>
    <citations>
      <citation type="res">Council Resolution No. SI-R17-012</citation>
    </citations>
    <history>
      <adopted>2016-05-23</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <preamble>At a duly called meeting of the Council of San Ildefonso Pueblo on the 
    23rd     day of            May        , 2016, the following Resolution was adopted:</preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Pueblo') is a sovereign and self-governing Tribe, recognized as such by the United States of America; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the voters of the Pueblo approved a Governing Agreement ("Agreement") for the Pueblo on November 19, 2011, and the Bureau of Indian Affairs approved the Agreement on December 21, 2011, pursuant to Federal law; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council is authorized to make laws for the Pueblo de San Ildefonso pursuant to Section 5 of the Agreement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council is authorized to make laws for the Pueblo pursuant to Section 5 of the Agreement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo is a party in the federal water adjudication State v. Aamodt, U.S. District Court of New Mexico No. 66CV6639; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>In 2006, after thirty-five years of litigation, and five years of negotiations, the Pueblo, the other three Pueblos, and other parties involved in the Aamodt case executed a Settlement Agreement (Jan. 19, 2006) to settle this water rights adjudication; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo, the United States and six other governments approved the Settlement Agreement (April 19, 2012) signed March 13, 2013 ("Revised Agreement") which includes terms required by the Settlement Act; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>as part of the Aamodt Litigation Settlement, the United States appropriated $15 million to the Pueblos Conservation Fund which the Office of Special Trustee , to be allocated as directed by the four Pueblos; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>terms contained in the Pueblo Economic Development Water Agreement signed by the four Pueblos were based on the Pueblo de San Ildefonso receiving Pojoaque Pueblo's share of the increased value of the Pueblo's Conservation Fund in exchange for waiving annual payments by the Pueblo of Pojoaque required by the Forbearance Agreement between the two Pueblos, which is one of the requirements of the Aamodt Litigation Settlement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Act and the Pueblo Economic Development Water Agreement signed July 18, 2013 by the Pueblo Governor, and Governors of the three other Pueblos in the Aamodt Litigation, provides over $6 million for use by the Pueblo, within the  limits specified in the Act; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Act at section 617(c), and 615(c)(7) allows the Pueblo to use these funds for any water related infrastructure activity "that is more cost-effective when implemented in conjunction with the construction of the Regional Water System, as determined by the Secretary [of the Interior];" and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council, pursuant to Resolution No. SI-R14-025 requested its first withdrawal from the Pueblo's Conservation Fund established by the Act in the amount of $1,200,000 and that request was partially approved by the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in the amount of $976,000, and disbursed by Office of Special Trustee (OST) to the Pueblo, and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council pursuant to Resolution No. SI-R14-035 requested its second withdrawal from the Pueblo's Conservation Fund established by the Act in the amount of $195,000 which was approved by the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in the amount of $195,000, and disbursed by OST to the Pueblo; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council pursuant to Resolution No. SI-R16-020 requested its third withdrawal from the Pueblo's Conservation Fund established by the Act in the amount of $1,200,000 which was approved by the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in the amount of $1,200,000, and disbursed by OST to the Pueblo; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>Additional work is needed to improve the Pueblo's ability to assist the environmental and design work needed for implementation of the Regional Water System; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Proposed Scope of Work and Budget (Expenditure Plan:  OST #4) of $744,289.00, which is Exhibit A to this resolution will benefit the Pueblo by the attached scope of work and budget for "Fourth Withdrawal of Aamodt Water Settlement Trust Funds from the Office of Special Trustee to Fund Aamodt Settlement Implementation Activities Requested by Pueblo Coordination with Regional Water System Work," and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the federal process for approving this request involves sending it to the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, for his approval; after that approval, it must be sent to the Northern Pueblos Agency for approval by the Superintendent to withdraw the amount specified in this Resolution; after that approval, the request goes to the Office of Special Trustee, which will transfer the money to the account designated by the Pueblo.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council authorizes and directs the Governor to take all steps necessary to implement this resolution, including signing all documents needed for withdrawal of funds in the amount of $744,289.00 from the Pueblo's share of the Pueblo Conservation Fund held by the federal Office of Special Trustee, and hiring and contracting for the purposes described in the attached Scope of Work and Budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council requests the United States to act quickly to implement the purposes of this resolution, and make funds available in the amount of $744,289.00 to implement the scope of work and budget attached as soon as possible.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on      May 23            , 2017, at a meeting with a vote of     7 	 in favor,    0    opposed,     0       abstaining and    3    absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <text>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE SPONSOR(S):    CR Perry Martinez</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
          <th>YES</th>
          <th>NO</th>
          <th>ABSTAIN</th>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Glenda Fred-Weahkee</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Terrence K. Garcia</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td>X</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Darryl Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td>X</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>M. Wayne Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td>X</td>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Perry Martinez</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Tim Martinez</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Christopher Moquino</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Donald Pena</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
          <td>X</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION TO THE GOVERNOR:</text>
    <text>Resolution No. SI-R17-012  was presented to the Governor of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso on the     23rd      day of         May     	, 2017, pursuant to the Governing document of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Agreement"), GOVERNOR, Sec. 4(c), and will become effective after signature by the Governor or veto override by the Council.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <subheading>GOVERNOR'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>{    } 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>{    }	VETO - RETURNED TO COUNCIL WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this ___________ day of ___________________, 2017.</text>
    <text>James R. Mountain, Governor</text>
    <text>Presented by the Governor to the Council on the ____ day of ____________, 2017.</text>
    <subheading>COUNCIL'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>Override of Governor's veto:</text>
    <text>{    } 	YES</text>
    <text>{    }	NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
          <th>YES</th>
          <th>NO</th>
          <th>ABSTAIN</th>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Glenda Fred-Weahkee</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Terrence K. Garcia</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Darryl Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>M. Wayne Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Perry Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Tim Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Christopher Moquino</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Donald Pena</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on _________________, 2017, at a meeting with a vote of ______ in favor, _____ opposed, _____ abstaining and _____ absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <attachment id="law">
    <text>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</text>
    <heading>Exhibit A</heading>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>Fourth Withdrawal of Aamodt Water Settlement Trust Funds</strong>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>
        <u>Expenditure Plan:  OST #4</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>Proposed Scope of Work</strong>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>Including Budget</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>
        <u>Exhibit A</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>ACT AUTHORIZING FOURTH WITHDRAWAL OF AAMODT WATER SETTLEMENT TRUST FUNDS FROM THE OFFICE OF SPECIAL TRUSTEE TO FUND </strong>
      <strong>
        <em>AAMODT</em>
      </strong>
      <strong> SETTLEMENT IMPLEMENTATION ACTIVITIES REQUESTED BY PUEBLO IN COORDINATION WITH REGIONAL WATER SYSTEM WORK</strong>
    </text>
    <text class="center">
      <strong>Proposed Scope of Work</strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Expenditure Plan:  OST #4</strong>
    </text>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <heading>Aamodt Litigation Settlement Act.</heading>
      <text>Public Law 111-291, Title VI is the Aamodt Litigation Settlement Act (ALSA).  Section 615.Aamodt Settlement Pueblos' Fund addresses use of $15 million mandatory appropriation described in Section 617(c) of ALSA ("Fund").  The Fund can be used for "rehabilitation, improvement, operation, maintenance, and replacement of the agricultural water delivery facilities, wastewater systems, and other water-related infrastructure of the applicable Pueblo" section 617(c)(1)(A)(i) of the ALSA.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tr proof="needed">
            <th proof="needed"/>
            <th proof="needed"/>
            <th>Amount</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1.</td>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p><u>Waste Water Treatment Plant Design</u>. The amount of $451,650 includes costs for <strong>Engineering Services of a MBR Design</strong> for the Waste water treatment plant design within the Pueblo de San Ildefonso boundaries. Funds will include the following:</p>
              <p>Task 1: Project Management and Meetings:</p>
              <p>Project Start-Up</p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Develop Project Management Plan (PMP)</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Work breakdown, resources and scope in PMP</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Project budget and project schedule</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Set up project files</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Establish contracts with subcontractors</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>Task 2: Geotech:</p>
              <p>On-site Geotech for foundation design</p>
              <p>Task 3: EPA-NPDES Permitting</p>
              <p>Submittal of NPDES permit for discharge to EPA</p>
              <p>Task 4: Survey and Base Map development</p>
              <p>Survey existing data colletion</p>
              <p>Establish local control points for project</p>
              <p>Survey lift station location and force mains</p>
              <p>WWTP site and boundary survey for plant</p>
              <p>Data Review and base map development</p>
              <p>Task 5: Pre-Bid and Select Membranes and support equipment</p>
              <p>Develop selection criteria with Pueblo</p>
              <p>Request bids from vendors</p>
              <p>Bid evaluation</p>
              <p>Recommendation</p>
              <p>Task 6: 30% design</p>
              <p>Design Criteria</p>
              <p>WWTP site plan</p>
              <p>Building plan (pre-engineered building)</p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Owner selected building plans incorporated</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>Grading and Drainage plan</p>
              <p>Effluent line P&amp;P</p>
              <p>Lift Station Plan</p>
              <p>Process flow and instrumentation plan</p>
              <p>Cost estimate refinement</p>
              <p>Task 7: 60%/90% design</p>
              <p>Updated plan sheets from 30% design</p>
              <p>Building Foundations</p>
              <p>Structures</p>
              <p>Mechanical process piping</p>
              <p>Utility</p>
              <p>Architectural</p>
              <p>Instrumentation and Controls</p>
              <p>Specifications and draft bid documents</p>
              <p>Cost estimate update</p>
              <p>Task 8: Final Design and Bid Documents</p>
              <p>Incorporate comments into plan set</p>
              <p>Plans and Spec document production</p>
            </td>
            <td>$451,650</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>2.</td>
            <td><u>Tribal Land Surveys</u>. The amount of $148,863.75 includes costs for surveying and working with the Pueblo, Bureau of Indian Affairs, Northern Pueblos, Housing Authority and Tribal Courts in the surveying tribal land assignments within the Pueblo de San Ildefonso boundaries. Funds for a licensed surveyor to finalize, research, analysis, and prepare boundary survey for San Ildefonso Tribal Land Assignments not included in Green Book.  Approximately 175 Assignments.  The survey includes plot record descriptions of tribal assignments and housing subdivisions, calculations of search corners, set supplemental control points, search for corners and begin boundary reconciliation.  Additionally, calculate refined search corners, perform second search, reconcile boundary and perform 3rd search where necessary.  Lastly, finalize boundary, perform drafting, check boundaries, and develop spreadsheet with all land assignments. The surveyor will work with Pueblo staff to update list to be current. Prepare survey plat that shows all land assignments. Set missing corners stamped with assignment information. Submit plat to Pueblo Natural Resources for review.</td>
            <td>$148,864</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>3.</td>
            <td><u>Operating Agreement</u>.  Daniel B. Stephens &amp; Associates, Inc. (DBS&amp;A) will prepare a draft operating agreement for the Pueblo de San Ildefonso. The Pueblo would like to develop a draft operating agreement to assist with understanding the operating and cost sharing discussions. Specific documents that include detail about OA include the Aamodt Litigation Settlement, Settlement Agreement, and Cost-Sharing and System Integration Agreement. DBS will prepare a draft operating agreement that at a minimum lists these requirements based on a draft agreement developed for the Navajo-Gallup Water Supply Project. DBS will review the Joint Powers Agreement, and will incorporate additional sections into the draft operating agreement. DBS will provide San Ildefonso Pueblo with a draft operating agreement for review.</td>
            <td>$15,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>4.</td>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p><u>Environmental Assessment (EA) for Wastewater and Phase I Project</u>.</p>
              <p>Preparing an Environmental Assessment (EA) and associated resource studies in support of Phase I of the Pueblo's proposed Wastewater Treatment Project. The EA will cover the wastewater project which would include the following major deliverables:</p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>A cultural resources survey report</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>A biological survey technical memorandum</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>A wetland/waterway report</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>An application for a Section 404 permit from the USACE</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>One Environmental Assessment that complies with RUS and BIA guidelines</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>The EA will include the following major deliverables:</p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Cultural Resources Investigations – This task includes the following subtasks: Pre-field preparation:</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>Compile existing data and associated GIS mapping from PBRWS project, and review new areas that need to be surveyed</p>
              <p>Field survey and documentation: Conduct a 100‐percent pedestrian field survey of the approximately 44 acres outside the PBRWS survey area, and document an estimated two new archaeological sites, the cemetery site near the proposed treatment location, and up to 10 historic buildings and/or acequias.</p>
              <p>Final cultural resources report: Prepare final report and associated forms Assumptions regarding the cultural resources investigations:</p>
              <p>The culture history, previous research, and methods sections of the report will be incorporated by referencing respective sections of the PBRWS Class III Cultural Resources Survey Report.</p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Biological &amp; Water Resources Investigations – This task includes the following subtasks:</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>Agency consultation and coordination: Coordinate with the USACE to determine requirements regarding waterway or wetland mapping for the proposed project and coordinate with appropriate federal agencies following completion of the field survey.</p>
              <p>Biological report: Prepare draft and final biological reports following the USDA biological report format</p>
              <p>Wetland report: Prepare a wetland/waterway report and associated USACE required documents: Clean Water Act  Section  404  permitting:  coordination with USACE, permit application and/or preconstruction notification.</p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Environmental Assessment – this task consists of preparing one environmental document that will comply with standards outlined by USDA‐RUS policies (RD Part 1970 A‐O) and BIA regulations (43 CFR 46.310) for environmental compliance. It includes the following subtasks: This task includes the following subtasks:</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
              <p>Scoping and consultation – Coordinate with Pueblo de San Ildefonso, USDA‐RUS, and BIA on report format and requirements</p>
              <p>Purpose and need, action alternatives, project considerations – Obtain appropriate information from the Pueblo of San Ildefonso, and derived from their contractors' data, including the GIS spatial data and the Preliminary Engineering Report. Develop a purpose and need statement and project description</p>
              <p>Draft report: Prepare resource descriptions, GIS mapping, resource forms, and compile document</p>
              <p>Agency consultation and revisions: Consult with appropriate review agencies and revise document</p>
              <p>Final document production: Prepare final report.</p>
            </td>
            <td>$39,275</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>5.</td>
            <td><u>Council Expenses:</u> Projected Council meetings; working sessions; Natural Resources Committee meetings; Cultural Affairs; Budget Committee; Mileage.</td>
            <td>$12,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>6.</td>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p><u>Legal support</u> for the Regional Water System, which includes evaluation, defense and affirmative action toward the implementation of a regional water system.</p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Legal expenses: legal services for activities relating to the implementation of the regional water system as well as ensuring Pueblo assets are protected from Santa Fe County which may include trespass which overlays the water systems.  Legal expenses and services for activities relating to Santa Fe County Trespass which overlays the water systems.</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
            </td>
            <td>$25,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>7.</td>
            <td><u>Contractor</u>.  The Pueblo has contracted Mark Duran to assist the Pueblo in transactions dealing with the stakeholders of the regional water system and opponents of the comprehensive water plan.</td>
            <td>$52,500</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>TOTAL</th>
            <th>$744,289</th>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </attachment>
</document>
