<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<document xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" id="Pueblo de San Ildefonso Res. No. SI-R17-037">
  <heading>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO COUNCIL RESOLUTION NO. SI-R17-037</heading>
  <law-heading>ACT AUTHORIZING SIXTH WITHDRAWAL OF AAMODT WATER SETTLEMENT TRUST FUNDS FROM THE OFFICE OF SPECIAL TRUSTEE TO FUND AAMODT SETTLEMENT IMPLEMENTATION ACTIVITIES REQUESTED BY PUEBLO IN COORDINATION WITH REGIONAL WATER SYSTEM WORK</law-heading>
  <meta>
    <citation type="res">Res. No. SI-R17-037</citation>
    <history>
      <adopted>October 31st, 2017</adopted>
    </history>
  </meta>
  <resolution-preamble>At a duly called meeting of the Council of San Ildefonso Pueblo on the 
    31st     day of            October        , 2017, the following Resolution was adopted:</resolution-preamble>
  <recitals>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Pueblo') is a sovereign and self-governing Tribe, recognized as such by the United States of America; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the voters of the Pueblo approved a Governing Agreement ("Agreement") for the Pueblo on November 19, 2011, and the Bureau of Indian Affairs approved the Agreement on December 21, 2011, pursuant to Federal law; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council is authorized to make laws for the Pueblo de San Ildefonso pursuant to Section 5 of the Agreement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Council is authorized to make laws for the Pueblo pursuant to Section 5 of the Agreement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo is a party in the federal water adjudication State v. Aamodt, U.S. District Court of New Mexico No. 66CV6639; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>In 2006, after thirty-five years of litigation, and five years of negotiations, the Pueblo, the other three Pueblos, and other parties involved in the Aamodt case executed a Settlement Agreement (Jan. 19, 2006) to settle this water rights adjudication; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo, the United States and six other governments approved the Settlement Agreement (April 19, 2012) signed March 13, 2013 ("Revised Agreement") which includes terms required by the Settlement Act; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>as part of the Aamodt Litigation Settlement, the United States appropriated $15 million to the Pueblo Conservation Fund through the Office of Special Trustee, to be allocated as directed by the four Pueblos; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>terms contained in the Pueblo Economic Development Water Agreement signed by the four Pueblos were based on the Pueblo de San Ildefonso receiving Pojoaque Pueblo's share of the increased value of the Pueblo Conservation Fund in exchange for waiving annual payments by the Pueblo of Pojoaque required by the Forbearance Agreement between the two Pueblos, which is one of the requirements of the Aamodt Litigation Settlement; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Act and the Pueblo Economic Development Water Agreement signed July 18, 2013 by the Pueblo Governor, and Governors of the three other Pueblos in the Aamodt Litigation, provides over $6 million for use by the Pueblo, within the  limits specified in the Act; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Act at section 617(c), and 615(c)(7) allows the Pueblo to use these funds for any water related infrastructure activity "that is more cost-effective when implemented in conjunction with the construction of the Regional Water System, as determined by the Secretary [of the Interior];" and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council, pursuant to Resolution No. SI-R14-025 requested its first withdrawal from the Pueblo Conservation Fund established by the Act in the amount of $1,200,000 and that request was partially approved by the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in the amount of $976,000, and disbursed by Office of Special Trustee (OST) to the Pueblo; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council pursuant to Resolution No. SI-R14-035 requested its second withdrawal from the Pueblo Conservation Fund established by the Act in the amount of $195,000 which was approved by the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in the amount of $195,000, and disbursed by OST to the Pueblo; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council pursuant to Resolution No. SI-R16-020 requested its third withdrawal from the Pueblo Conservation Fund established by the Act in the amount of $1,200,000 which was approved by the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in the amount of $1,200,000, and disbursed by OST to the Pueblo; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council pursuant to Resolution No. SI-R17-012 requested its fourth withdrawal from the Pueblo's Conservation Fund established by the Act in the amount of $744,289, which was partially approved by the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in the amount of $517,925, and disbursed by OST to the Pueblo; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Tribal Council pursuant to Resolution No. SI-R17-012 resubmitted a fifth withdrawal from the Pueblo's Conservation Fund established by the Act in the amount of $226,354 which was approved by the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs in the amount of $226,354, and disbursed by OST to the Pueblo; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso, to-date, has withdrawn a total amount of $3,111,279 from the Pueblo Conservation Fund established by the Act in which the Pueblo used these funds water related infrastructure activity "that is more cost-effective when implemented in conjunction with the construction of the Regional Water System; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Pueblo de San Ildefonso is preparing to improve the Pueblo's ability to assist the environmental, design and construction work needed for implementation of the Regional Water System; and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the Scope of Work and Budget of $4,000,000.00 (Expenditure Plan: OST #6), which is Exhibit A to this resolution, will benefit the Pueblo by the attached scope of work and budget for "Sixth Withdrawal of Aamodt Water Settlement Trust Funds from the Office of Special Trustee to Fund Aamodt Settlement Implementation Activities Requested by Pueblo Coordination with Regional Water System Work," and</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>WHEREAS,</conjunction>
      <text>the federal process for approving this request involves sending it to the Regional Director of the Bureau of Indian Affairs, for his approval; after that approval, it must be sent to the Northern Pueblos Agency for approval by the Superintendent to withdraw the amount specified in this Resolution; after that approval, the request goes to the Office of Special Trustee, which will transfer the money to the account designated by the Pueblo.</text>
    </recital>
    <recital>
      <conjunction>NOW THEREFORE BE IT RESOLVED</conjunction>
      <text>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council authorizes and directs the Governor to take all steps necessary to implement this resolution, including signing all documents needed for withdrawal of funds in the amount of $4,000,000.00 from the Pueblo's share of the Pueblo Conservation Fund held by the federal Office of Special Trustee, and hiring and contracting for the purposes described in the attached Scope of Work and Budget.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The Pueblo de San Ildefonso Council requests the United States to act quickly to implement the purposes of this resolution, and make funds available in the amount of $4,000,000.00 to implement the scope of work and budget attached as soon as possible.</text>
      </para>
    </recital>
  </recitals>
  <procedural-data>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on      October 31            , 2017, at a meeting with a vote of       	 in favor,	    opposed,	        abstaining and	      absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <text>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE SPONSOR(S):    Council Representative Perry Martinez</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
          <th>YES</th>
          <th>NO</th>
          <th>ABSTAIN</th>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Glenda Fred-Weahkee</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Terrence K. Garcia</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Darryl Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>M. Wayne Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Perry Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Tim Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Christopher Moquino</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Donald Pena</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>DELIVERY OF THE RESOLUTION TO THE GOVERNOR:</text>
    <text>Resolution No. SI-R17-037  was presented to the Governor of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso on the     31st      day of        October     	, 2017, pursuant to the Governing document of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso ("Agreement"), GOVERNOR, Sec. 4(c), and will become effective after signature by the Governor or veto override by the Council.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
    <subheading>GOVERNOR'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>{    } 	APPROVED</text>
    <text>{    }	VETO - RETURNED TO COUNCIL WITH EXPLANATION:</text>
    <text>On this ___________ day of ___________________, 2017.</text>
    <text>James R. Mountain, Governor</text>
    <text>Presented by the Governor to the Council on the ____ day of ____________, 2017.</text>
    <subheading>COUNCIL'S ACTION:</subheading>
    <text>Override of Governor's veto:</text>
    <text>{    } 	YES</text>
    <text>{    }	NO</text>
    <text>
      <table>
        <tr>
          <th>COUNCIL REPRESENTATIVE</th>
          <th>YES</th>
          <th>NO</th>
          <th>ABSTAIN</th>
          <th>ABSENT</th>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Glenda Fred-Weahkee</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Terrence K. Garcia</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Thomas Gonzales</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Darryl Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>M. Wayne Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Perry Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Tim Martinez</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Christopher Moquino</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Donald Pena</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
        <tr>
          <td>Irene Tse-Pe</td>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
          <td/>
        </tr>
      </table>
    </text>
    <text>CERTIFICATION</text>
    <text>The foregoing resolution was duly voted upon by the Council on _________________, 2017, at a meeting with a vote of ______ in favor, _____ opposed, _____ abstaining and _____ absent (Governor presiding and not voting) pursuant to the authority vested in the Council by the Agreement of the Pueblo de San Ildefonso.</text>
    <text>Irene Tse-Pe, Council Secretary</text>
  </procedural-data>
  <attachment id="law">
    <text>PUEBLO DE SAN ILDEFONSO</text>
    <text>Exhibit A</text>
    <text>
      <center>
        <strong>Sixth Withdrawal of Aamodt Water Settlement Trust Funds</strong>
      </center>
    </text>
    <text>
      <center>
        <strong>
          <u>Expenditure Plan:  OST #6</u>
        </strong>
      </center>
    </text>
    <text>
      <center>
        <strong>Proposed Scope of Work</strong>
      </center>
    </text>
    <text>
      <center>
        <strong>Including Budget</strong>
      </center>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>
        <u>Exhibit A</u>
      </strong>
    </text>
    <text>
      <center>
        <strong>ACT AUTHORIZING SIXTH WITHDRAWAL OF AAMODT WATER SETTLEMENT TRUST FUNDS FROM THE OFFICE OF SPECIAL TRUSTEE TO FUND </strong>
        <strong>
          <em>AAMODT</em>
        </strong>
        <strong> SETTLEMENT IMPLEMENTATION ACTIVITIES REQUESTED BY PUEBLO IN COORDINATION WITH REGIONAL WATER SYSTEM WORK</strong>
      </center>
    </text>
    <text>
      <center>
        <strong>Proposed Scope of Work</strong>
      </center>
    </text>
    <text>
      <strong>Expenditure Plan:  OST #6</strong>
    </text>
    <para>
      <num>1.</num>
      <heading>Aamodt Litigation Settlement Act.</heading>
      <text>Public Law 111-291, Title VI is the Aamodt Litigation Settlement Act (ALSA).  Section 615.Aamodt Settlement Pueblos' Fund addresses use of $15 million mandatory appropriation described in Section 617(c) of ALSA ("Fund").  The Fund can be used for "rehabilitation, improvement, operation, maintenance, and replacement of the agricultural water delivery facilities, wastewater systems, and other water-related infrastructure of the applicable Pueblo" section 617(c)(1)(A)(i) of the ALSA.</text>
      <text>
        <table>
          <tr proof="needed">
            <th proof="needed"/>
            <th proof="needed"/>
            <th>Amount</th>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>1.</td>
            <td><u>Construction of Waste Water Treatment Plant and Distribution System</u>. The amount of $3,500,000 includes costs for <strong>Construction</strong> of a Waste Water treatment plant and Distribution System within the Pueblo de San Ildefonso boundaries. A Collection System Design (Plans, Contract Documents and Technical Specifications) for the Pueblo Center &amp; South is complete. The design was completed in December 2016 and the Pueblo is ready for bidding and construction, with funding.  The project has the support of the Tribal Government, Council and Community.  A Preliminary Engineering Report (PER) was completed prior to the collection system design. This proposed project is Phase 1 of the Recommended Alternative identified in the PER which was completed in September 2016.  A Preliminary Opinion of Probable Construction Costs was prepared by a licensed engineer during the system design.  As such and per the ALSA ("Fund"), the Fund can be used for " replacement of a wastewater systems.  Thus, the Pueblo will use its funds for a new sewer collection system for the Pueblo South which is approximately 2.8 miles of new PVC sewer pipe and 4 lift stations, serving 39 homes (approximately 106 people).  Rehabilitation of existing VCP by pipe bursting, approximately 2.6 miles of new HDPE pipe, serving 134 homes (approximately 365 people).  The Pueblo hopes that a new Waste Water Collection System will protect the investment of the PBRWS by reducing the risk of contamination to the aquifer.</td>
            <td>$3,400,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>2.</td>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p><u>Project Engineer</u>.  Engineer will support PSI with program management responsibilities by outlining objectives, planning execution, managing operations, and reporting on status of individual projects; Review PBRWS Environmental Impact Statement prepared by the U.S. Department of the Interior Bureau of Reclamation, Upper Colorado Region and provide comments regarding the proposed action as it relates to PSI;  Review the PBRWS Basis of Design Report (BDR) prepared by CDM Smith, dated August 4, 2018 and provide comments regarding design approach, applicable criteria and standards, performance requirements and material selection that is proposed to be utilized for the project. E&amp;S will review and provide comments relative to the following for general conformance to the overall project goals and desires of PSI:</p>
              <p>Water Quality and Regulations;</p>
              <p>Permits;</p>
              <p>Raw Water Intake System;</p>
              <p>Water Transmission and Distribution;</p>
              <p>Integration of Existing Infrastructure;</p>
              <p>Water Treatment Process Facilities;</p>
              <p>WTP Site Development;</p>
              <p>Architectural Design;</p>
              <p>Structural Design Criteria;</p>
              <p>Heating, Ventilation, and Air Conditioning;</p>
              <p>Plumbing;</p>
              <p>Fire Protection – Treatment Building;</p>
              <p>Electrical Design;</p>
              <p>Instrumentation and Control; and</p>
              <p>Telecommunications and Security</p>
              <p>Review 30% and 60% design drawings for proposed system component selections, locations, and ancillaries for the intake, raw water transmission pipeline, water treatment plant, finished water transmission pipelines, distribution pipelines, and storage tanks.  Review the proposed disposal options for the sanitary and brine wastes and standby power at the Water Treatment Plant; Preparation of review comments utilizing the Excel Comment Response Form provided by CDM Smith; Attend Stakeholder Meetings (In-Person or by teleconference): This task includes attending meetings and responding to correspondence initiated and scheduled by PSI and general coordination necessary to complete the work for the assigned task. Attend 30% and 60% Stakeholder Design Workshop(s); Prepare responses on behalf of PSI to Design Team requests for information; Perform review of comparison of alternatives and evaluations prepared by others regarding PBRWS, and provide recommendations regarding need for further information and/or courses of action for PSI to undertake. Prepare requests for additional information, design changes, or other modifications to the project layout, design, operations, and maintenance on behalf of PSI, upon PSI approval of the nature and content of these requests as submitted to PSI prior to forwarding to external parties. Maintain an active list of issues and their disposition through the course of the project phases under contract between PSI and E&amp;S.  Communicate to PSI the outstanding issues which need PSI attention.</p>
            </td>
            <td>$145,500</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>3.</td>
            <td><u>Precision Surveys</u>. The amount of $38,643 includes costs for assisting the Pueblo with surveying data, maps and interaction with the Pueblo, Bureau of Indian Affairs, PBRWS Pueblos and local entities regarding the Pueblos general survey and project infrastructure projects.</td>
            <td>$156,890</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
            <td proof="needed"/>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>4.</td>
            <td><u>Operating Agreement</u>.  Daniel B. Stephens &amp; Associates, Inc. (DBS) will be managing and assisting the Pueblo with drafting, editing an Operating Agreement (OA) for the Pueblo de San Ildefonso. The Pueblo has developed a draft operating agreement and will need assistance with understanding the operating and cost sharing discussions. Specific documents that include detail about OA include the Aamodt Litigation Settlement, Settlement Agreement, and Cost-Sharing and System Integration Agreement. DBS will assist Pueblo with the review of the Joint Powers Agreement, and will incorporate additional sections into the draft operating agreement.</td>
            <td>$21,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>5.</td>
            <td><u>Blue Dove Road design</u>.  Obtain aerial photogrammetry and site mapping data necessary to complete the topography survey data needed for drainage investigation and roadway alignment. Site mapping filled and extended to the south and extended mapping to the northeast.  An investigation to determine site subsurface conditions, and based upon the conditions encountered, develop geotechnical recommendations for: shallow foundations, foundation bearing pressures, site grading, drainage and earthwork.  To accomplish  these, objectives  test holes will be drilled and logged, soil samples will be obtained for laboratory testing of the selected samples for moisture content, dry density, particle size analysis and consolidation. Preparation of a detailed report presenting the results of the field and laboratory investigations and geotechnical recommendations for the site will be developed and signed by a registered engineer. Preparation of a Drainage Report as required, final Grading Plan with work estimates for the effort to provide balanced site conditions for grading approval, storm sewer analysis, downstream capacity analysis and identification of any offsite drainage issues and finished contours. An import/export calculation will be performed and provided to the owners upon request. Conduct and/or attend bi-weekly coordination and progress meetings to discuss project's status and any construction issues</td>
            <td>$55,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>6.</td>
            <td><u>Irrigation Well survey, maintenance and rehabilitation of Wells</u>.</td>
            <td>$25,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>7.</td>
            <td><u>Project Manager</u>.  The Pueblo has contracted a Project Manager oversees, manages and is providing for the preparation of the regional water system that is within the Pueblo's exterior boundaries.  In addition, the contractor has managed multiple infrastructure initiatives that correlate and parallel the RWS, such as the waste water, roads, fiber optics, natural gas, and water.  The contractor oversees, manages, and coordinates all utility and infrastructure activities related to the RWS. This will maximize the benefit of the Regional Water System, and assist Reclamation in design of the portion of this system to be located within Pueblo lands.</td>
            <td>$96,110</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>8.</td>
            <td><u>Council Expenses:</u> Projected Council meetings, working sessions, Natural Resources Committee meetings, Cultural Affairs, Budget Committee, and Mileage.</td>
            <td>$37,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>9.</td>
            <td proof="needed">
              <p><u>Legal support</u> for the Regional Water System, which includes evaluation, defense and affirmative action toward the implementation of a regional water system.</p>
              <p>
                <text>
                  <ul proof="needed">
                    <li>Legal expenses: legal services for activities relating to the implementation of the regional water system as well as ensuring Pueblo assets are protected from Santa Fe County which may include trespass which overlays the water systems.  Legal expenses and services for activities relating to Santa Fe County Trespass which overlays the water systems.</li>
                  </ul>
                </text>
              </p>
            </td>
            <td>$62,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <td>10.</td>
            <td><u>Administration</u> for the Regional Water System, which includes accounting and general expenses.</td>
            <td>$54,000</td>
          </tr>
          <tr>
            <th>TOTAL</th>
            <th>$4,000,000</th>
          </tr>
        </table>
      </text>
    </para>
  </attachment>
</document>
